ESMAEIL REZAEI

May 2024 Available | Green Card Holder | Dec 2024 Graduate

a +1 (857) 376-9504

⊠ ishmaelrezaei@gmail.com

★ 411 Allen st, New Bedford, MA-02740

• https://github.com/ishmaelrezaei
• https://ishmaelrezaei.github.io
http://www.linkedin.com/in/esmaeil-rezaei

SUMMARY

A talented, passionate and self motivated data scientist with 1 year and 5 months experience. PhD student in Computational Science, M.S. in Data Science, M.S. in Socio-Economic System Engineering, and B.S. in Mathematics. Proficient in Python, R, SQL, SAS

SKILLS

• Python (Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow, Pyspark, Keras, Jupyter)

• R (ggplot2, tidyverse)

• **AWS** (SageMaker)

• Microsoft Power BI (Dashboard development, App)

• SQL (SQL language, MySQL, Erwin)

Other: Excel • PowerPoint • Matplotlib • Seaborn • spark • Matlab • parallel processing Familiar C++, Hadoop, LATRX

ML Proficiencies: Applied Machine Learning • Regression • Dimensionality Reduction • Optimization • Classification • Clustering • Deep Learning • CNN • CART • XGBoost • Statistics • Probability • Data Mining

WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Researcher, University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth, (Sep 2021 - Present)

Research Assistant

- Coded using PySpark library in Python, SAS, and Tableau to analyze 180M data of Michelin company (PySpark, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Tableau, SAS).
- Developed an advanced driving assistance system with 92% accuracy of recognition for US Department of Transportation, coded in Python and tested on a driving simulator (Pyspark, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn).
- Reduced computational cost of PCA by 78 times through developing an advanced machine learning algorithm, coded Python
 and Matlab scripts to build the algorithm, and evaluated its performance in different scripts.

Teaching Assistant

• Tutored 35 students with learning challenges in coding up engineering solutions with Matlab, Python.

Data Scientist, Behin Tadbir Paradise, (Feb 2020 - Jul 2021)

■ Built insurance pricing algorithms for financial services using machine learning (XGBoost, Naive Bayes, Neural Networks), coded in Python, and collaborated with software developers to create the **GUI**, significantly improved expected revenue.

Founder and Manager, SHARIFNEGAR, (Nov 2015 - Aug 2021)

• Led a team of 60 in an e-commerce website to sell tutorials in Data Science, Data Analytics, Mathematics, and Engineering.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Computational Science and Engineering	Sep 2021 - Dec 2024	
University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth	GPA 3.94	
Master of Science in Data Science University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth	Sep 2021 - May 2024 GPA 4.0	
Master of Science in Industrial Engineering (Socio-Economic Engineering option) University of Science and Technology of Mazandaran, Iran	Sep 2013 - Sep 2015 GPA 3.61	
Bachelor of Science in Pure Mathematics Velayat University, Iran	Jan 2009 - Jul 2012 GPA 3.05	

PROJECTS

National Science Foundation (NSF) Funded Projects

- Developed a machine learning algorithm for demand forecasting in the ComEd supply chain (State of Illinois). Coded in Python,
 R, and SQL scripts for building the algorithm, data cleaning, data wrangling, and handling noisy data. Utilized Tableau and Microsoft Power BI for data visualizations, including charts, dashboards, and custom reports.
- Develop a super-fast dimensionality reduction algorithm for big data. Coded Python and Matlab scripts to implement the algorithm, and perform data process, data visualization, data analytics.

Michelin North America Inc Funded Projects

• Conducted data analysis (180 million data), data cleaning using Microsoft Power BI and Tableau. Worked in a team of Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), University of Massachusetts, and Michelin engineers (Pyspark, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn).

US Department of Transportation Funded Project

 Develop a advanced driving assistance system to improve driving safety. The algorithm implemented successfully, coded Python, data analytics, data cleaning, and data visualization (Pyspark, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn).

MISCELLANEOUS

■ Mentored several successful graduate students in conducting research